<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="otto_dock_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2026 Otto Contributors

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="dock item management protocol">
    This protocol allows clients to provide elements for the Otto
    compositor's dock area.
    </description>

  <interface name="otto_dock_manager_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="manager for creating dock items">
      The dock manager global allows clients to create dock items.
    </description>
    
    <enum name="error">
      <description summary="protocol errors">
        These errors can be emitted in response to otto_dock_manager_v1 requests.
      </description>
      <entry name="role" value="0" summary="surface already has a role"/>
      <entry name="invalid_surface" value="1" summary="invalid surface"/>
    </enum>
    <request name="get_dock_item">
      <description summary="get dock item by application identifier">
        Get the dock item for a specific application by its app_id.
        Returns null if no dock item exists for the given app_id.

        This allows applications to find and interact with their dock
        representation without needing to track the otto_dock_item_v1
        object from assign_layer_to_dock.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="otto_dock_item_v1"/>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string" summary="application identifier"/>
    </request>
    

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the dock manager">
        Destroy the dock manager object. This does not affect existing dock items.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="otto_dock_item_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="a dock item">
      A dock item represents an element in the Otto compositor's dock. It is associated with a specific
      application (identified by app_id).
      
      The item can have a preview surface that displays the application's content,
      as well as optional badge text and a progress indicator.
      The compositor manages the layout and presentation of dock items,
      including grouping by app_id and handling interactions.
    </description>

    <request name="set_preview">
      <description summary="set or replace the preview surface">
        Set or replace the preview surface that displays the dock item's content.
        This allows applications to provide custom rendering (e.g., live video
        playback, custom icons, etc.) while the main surface retains the ability
        to have popups attached.

        The compositor validates that the provided `wl_surface` (or its
        backing surface) is owned or authorized by the client that controls
        this dock item (or otherwise permitted for the `app_id`). If the
        compositor cannot verify ownership or authorization, the request may
        be rejected. The surface should be a child of the main surface
        provided during dock item creation.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface" allow-null="true"
           summary="the surface to use as preview, or null to clear"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_badge">
      <description summary="set badge text for the dock item">
        Set a badge label to be displayed on the dock item. This is typically
        used to show notification counts, status indicators, or other short
        text overlays (similar to macOS dock badges).

        The compositor will render the badge text over the dock item's preview.
        Pass an empty string or null to clear the badge.
      </description>
      <arg name="text" type="string" allow-null="true"
           summary="badge text to display, or null to clear"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_progress">
      <description summary="set progress indicator for the dock item">
        Set a progress indicator to be displayed on the dock item. This is
        typically rendered as a progress bar or pie chart overlay on the
        dock item (similar to macOS dock progress indicators).

        The value should be between 0.0 (no progress) and 1.0 (complete).
        Pass a negative value to hide the progress indicator.
      </description>
      <arg name="value" type="fixed"
           summary="progress value from 0.0 to 1.0, or negative to clear"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
